Guide to the Crew (Rowing) Records 1975-2011
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Crew (Rowing) Records
1975-2011
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 359
1 Linear foot of shelf space 2 boxes
Organized crew at Washington State University began as a men's club sport in the 1969-1970 school year; female Cougars began rowing in 1974. The collection consists of papers dealing with men's and women's crew at Washington State University. They tend not to be official university papers, but rather documents collected by people affiliated with the programs, though some official budgets and other materials are included.
Organized crew at Washington State University began as a men's club sport in the 1969-1970 school year; female Cougars began rowing in 1974. In 1990, women's rowing became an official university-funded sport; as of 2016 men's rowing still remains a club activity. The terms crew and rowing are effectively interchangeable.
The collection consists of papers dealing with men's and women's crew at Washington State University. They tend not to be official university papers, but rather documents collected by people affiliated with the programs, though some official budgets and other materials are included. The materials bulk from about 1985-2000, with the majority of the club materials dating from 1985-1989. Very little men's materials, other than the Pull Hard newsletters, are present from 1990 forward.
The collection is broken into two primary series. The first series deals with crew as a club sport, and deals primarily, but not exclusively, with men's rowing. It contains one short subseries of materials from the Cougar Rowing Association / Cougar Rowing Foundation, which served as a fund-raising, organizational, and alumni group for the men's and women's clubs. The second series is women's rowing from 1990 (when it became an official university sport) forward. The bulk of that is a subseries consisting of clippings and small materials such as schedules, programs, and results. All the materials are organized alphabetically by subject save one subseries - the women's rowing clippings and other small materials are organized chronologically and placed at the end of the women's crew materials. There is some slight overlap between the series - for example, "Results: PAC-10 Championships and San Diego Crew Classic, 1997-2001" includes both women's athletics and men's club results.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The materials in this collection were transferred to MASC by Roger and Tammy Crawford on March 16, 2016, and retained as accession UA2016-03. Roger and Tammy both rowed for WSU in the 1980s; Tammy coached women's crew from 1990-2002.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University -- Rowing
Rowing -- Washington (State) -- Pullman; Women rowers -- Washington (State) -- Pullman; Rowers -- Washington (State) -- Pullman
Sports and Recreation; Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
- Series 1: Crew (as a club sport - primarily men's, but not exclusively)
  - Bylaws: Men's Crew, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Christy Cook, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1978-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coeur d'Alene Regatta Planning, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 1.1: Cougar Rowing Association / Cougar Rowing Foundation
    - Bylaws and Incorporation, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fundraising and Membership, 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Crew Histories, 1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dedication: Ken Abbey Shellhouse, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Master's Camp Outline, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newsletter: The Pull Hard, 1977-2011 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oars for Sale, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Results: PAC-10 Championships and San Diego Crew Classic, 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Safety Program, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Women's Crew Club Officers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 2: Women's Rowing (as an official sport, not as a club)
  - Budgets, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Coaching Application and Information: Tammy Crawford, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Media Guides, 1992-2009 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Newsletter: Cougar Rowing, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1995 ca. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2.1: Women's Crew Clippings, Programs, Results, Schedules, etc.
    - Clippings, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Programs and Schedules/Results, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Clippings and Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Programs and Schedules/Results, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Programs, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Clippings, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Schedule, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Clippings, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Clippings, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Clippings and Fund-Raising, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Programs, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Clippings, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)